. In this video I'm going to show how we
这段视频中 我们来看如何先用
can first learn a deep belief net by stacking up restricted Boltzmann
堆叠受限玻尔兹曼机的方式 学习一个深度信念网络
machines. And then we can treat that as a deep
然后将其视为一个
neural net that we fine tune discriminatory.
可以进行判别性微调的深度神经网络
So instead of fine tuning it to be better at generation, as we did in the previous
并非如上一个视频中的 调优使其更好地生成数据
video, we're going to fine tune it to be better at discriminating between classes.
而是更好地区分不同类别
This works very well and led to a big renewal of interest in neural networks.
这个方法效果非常好 它引发了神经网络的一次巨大复兴
In speech recognition, it's had a major influence and many leading groups are now
在语音识别中它具有相当的影响力
switching to using deep neural nets in order to reduce the error rate, in speech
许多主要的研究组现在转而 使用深度神经网络来降低错误率
recognition. I now want to talk about fine tuning
我现在想探讨一下让深度网络 更擅长判别的调优过程
So we first learn one layer of features at a time, by stacking up restricted
首先从堆叠RBM开始逐层学习特征
Boltzmann machines. Then we treat this as pre-training that
该过程即为DBN网络 寻找一组好的初始权重
finds a good initial set of weights in the DPO network and we fine tune those
接下来我们
weights using some local search procedure.
使用一些局部搜索过程进行调优
In the previous video I showed you how to use contrustive weight sleep to fine tune
上一个视频中展示了如何使用 "wake-sleep" 对比调优
a deep network so that it was better generating its inputs.
从而使深度网络生成输入的能力更强
In this video we're going to use back propagation to fine tune a model to be
这节视频中使用反向传播调优一个模型
better at discrimination. If we do this it overcomes many of the
令其在判别中做的更好 这样能够克服反向传播
standard limitations of back propagation. It makes it much easier to learn deep
反向传播的一些常规限制 深度网络的学习更容易了
nets. And it makes those nets generalise
泛化能力也更好
better. We need to understand why back
我们需要理解为什么预训练权重之后
propagation when we pre-train the weights.
为什么预训练权重之后要做反向传播
And there's really two effects. There's an effect on optimization and
有两个效应 一个与优化有关
there's an effect on generalization. So the pre-training scales really well if
另一个与泛化有关 预训练在训练大型网络上
we have big networks, especially if each layer has locality.
效果很好 尤其是当每一层都有局部性时
So if we're doing vision, for example, and we had local receptor fields in each
以视觉为例 每一层都有局部感受野
layer, then there's not much interaction between widely separate locations.
这样在分隔较远的区域之间就不会互相干涉了
And so it's very easy to learn a big layer more or less in parallel.
并且 并行学习一个很大的层比较容易
When we do pre-training. We don't start back propagation until
预训练时 直到已经学得合适的
we've already learned sensible feature detectors.
已经学得合适的特征检测器之后 才开始反向传播
And these feature detectors should be very helpful for discrimination.
这些特征检测器对于判别很有帮助
So the initial gradients are much more sensible than if we use random ones.
所以这样的初始梯度相对随机值更为合理
And back propagation doesn't need to do a global search.
反向传播也不需要做全局搜索
It just needs to do a local search from a sensible starting point.
而只需从一个合理的起点开始局部搜索即可
In addition to being easier to optimize, pre-trained nets exhibit much less
除了更容易优化 预训练网络的过拟合水平也更低
overfitting. That's because most of the information in
这是因为最终权重中的多数信息
the final weights comes from modeling the distribution of input vectors.
来自对输入向量分布的建模
And these input vectors, if you're dealing with something like images,
这些输入向量 比如图片
generally contain a lot more information than labels.
显然比单纯的标签包含了更多信息
A label typically only contains a few bits of information to constrain the
标签仅仅带有很少的比特
mapping from input to output. Whereas an image contains a lot of
已经学得合适的表示从输入到输出的映射
information which will constrain any generative model of a set of images.
然而图片携带了大量信息 可以构建一组图片的生成模型
The information in the labels is only used for the final fine tuning And
标签中的信息仅仅用来做最后的调优
because by that stage we've already decided on the feature detectors, we're
因为此时我们已经确定了特征检测器
not squandering that precious information designing feature detectors from scratch.
我们不再浪费之前的信息以设计特征检测器
The fine tuning only makes slight changes to the feature detectors we learned in
调优仅仅对在生成预训练阶段学到的
the generative pre-training phase. And those are the changes required to get
预训练阶段学到的特征检测器做微调 这些微调是
the category boundaries in the right place.
这些微调是得到正确的类别边界所必需的
The important thing is the back propagation is not being required to
需要强调 反向传播不是用来发现新特征的
discover new features. And so it doesn't need nearly as much
发现新特征的 所以它不需要太多的标签数据
label data. In fact, this type of learning works well
事实上 这种学习方式对于 大量不带标签的数据非常有效
when most of the data is unlabeled, because the generative pre-training can
因为生成性预训练可以很好地利用这些数据
make use of the light data. The unlabeled data is still very useful
不带标签的数据对于发现好的特征仍然非常有用
for discovering good features. There is an obvious objection to this
仍然非常有用 对于这种学习方法
type of learning, which is that when we do generative pre-training.
一种常见的异议是 生成性预训练
We'll be learning lots of features that are useless for the particular
生成性预训练学到了大量 与判别任务无关的特征
discriminative task we want the net to do.
这对我们想让网络做的事情没有用处
Consider, for example, that you might want the net to discriminate between
比如你想让网络区分不同的形状
shapes or you might want the net to discriminate between different poses of
或者区分一种形状的不同姿态
one shape. They need very different features, and if
它们需要迥然不同的特征
you don't know the task in advance. You'll inevitably learn features that are
如果你提前并不知道任务是什么 你会不可避免地学到
never used. When computers were much smaller, that
学到一些永远用不上的特征 电脑性能差的时候
was the serious objection. But now that computers are large enough,
这是很严重的问题 但现在的电脑性能足够强大
we can afford to learn features that are never used.
我们能够承受学习多余特征的代价
And, we can afford it because among all the features we learn, there will be some
因为在我们学到的所有特征中
that are much more useful than their raw inputs.
总有一些特征远比 它们的原始输入有用
And that more than makes up for the fact that we have learned some features that
这在很大程度上弥补了
aren't helpful for the particular task we're interested in.
学到一些无关特征的问题
So let's apply this to modeling the m-list digits.
来看看对 MNIST 数据集的应用情况
We'll now learn three hidden layers of features entirely unsupervised.
现在完全非监督地学习了三个特征隐层
Once we've done that learning, when we generate from the model,
一旦完成了学习 从模型中就能够生成
it will generate things that look like real digits.
看上去像真的数字的图像
And it'll generate them from all the different classes.
它能从所有不同的类别中生成
And it'll typically take a while before it switches from one class to another.
从一类换到另一类
And it will typically take a while before it switches from one class to another
只需要一会儿
because it'll tend to stay in the same ravine for a while before it jumps to
因为它从一个"山谷"跳向另一个时
another ravine. But the question is, are the features
需要停留一段时间 问题在于
that we've learned that way useful for doing discrimination?
这些特征对于判别任务有用处吗？
So all we need to do is add a final 10-way soft max at the top.
只需要添加在最后添加 一个十路softmax层
And fine tune it with back propagation. And see if we do better than purely
然后用反向传播进行调优即可
discriminative training. So here's the results on the permutation
看看是不是比单纯的判别性训练有效
invariant M-ness task. And what I mean is permutation invariant
这是置换不变的MNIST任务 置换不变的意思是
is, if we were to apply a fixed random permutation to all the pixels, the same
如果对所有像素做固定的随机置换
permutation to every test and training case, the results of our algorithm
包括所有的测试和训练样例
wouldn't change. That's clearly not true for something
算法的结果不会改变 这对于卷积网络显然是不成立的
like a convolutional net. A convolutional net's been told something
如果对卷积网络使用这种置换
about the task. By applying this fixed permutation, we
就毁掉了所有卷积网络学到的
destroy all simple ways of telling the net something about the spatial nature of
与任务相关的空间特性
the task. So if you apply standard back
使用一般的反向传播
propagation. It's hard to do better than 1.6% errors.
错误率很难低于 1.6%
John Platt and myself have both tried quite hard applying standard back
John Platt 和我都艰难尝试过 对许多不同的网络结构
propagation with various different architectures.
使用标准的反向传播算法
And we're both quite good at doing it. You can actually beat 1.6%.
我们都很擅长这件事 事实上
By using constraints on the incoming weight vectors of the hidden units.
通过限制隐层权重向量的长度 你可以超过 1.6%的结果
If you use an appropriate restriction on the length of an incoming weight vector,
这样的限制会使结果稍好于 1.6%
you can do a bit better than 1.6%. Support vector machines can get 1.4
支持向量机可以做到 1.4%
percent. And this was one of the pieces of
而这也是支持向量机
evidence that led to support vector machines, supplanting back propagation.
支持向量机取代反向传播算法的理由之一
If you pretrain a network using a stack of Boltzmann Machines.
如果你使用堆叠玻尔兹曼机 预训练一个网络
And then you fine tune it to be better at generating the joint density of digits
然后调优让它更好地 生成数字和标签的联合密度
and image labels. Then you can get down to 1.25%.
这样你可以降到 1.25%
If you train a stack of Boltzmann machines, and simply put a 10-way
如果你训练堆叠玻尔兹曼机 接着在顶部
[INAUDIBLE] on top, and fine tune it. You can get to 1.15%.
放置一个十路softmax输出 然后调优 你会得到 1.15%
And with more fiddling around, you can get that down to about one%.
再做一些微调 可以降到 1%
So you can do a lot better than standard back propagation.
所以这比使用标准的反向传播好得多
And also better than support vector machines by using generative pre-training
也比 SVM 好
followed by discriminative fine tuning. Mackerie Yerenzato working in Yan
Yan LeCun 组的 Mackerie Yerenzato 表明
LeCanne's group also showed, using a slightly different pre-training method,
使用一种稍微不同的预训练方法
that pre-training helps for models that have more data and better prions.
能让模型有 更多的数据和更好的先验
So they used an additional 60,000 distorted digital images.
他们使用了另外六万张失真的数字图片
So they had a lot more training data. They also used convolution multilinear
这样训练数据就多了很多 他们还使用了卷积多线性网络
network. And Yan's group is the best group, at
Yan的组是调制这类网络最好的组
tuning those. With back propagation, they managed to
使用反向传播 他们把错误率降到了 0.49%
get down to.49%. When they did the unsupervised layer by
他们做非监督逐层预训练然后调优的时候
layer pre-training, followed by back propagation they got down to.39%.
错误率降到了 0.39%
Which at the time was a record. So you may remember this picture from the
当时这是一项纪录 所以你可能记得
first lecture. This was one of the examples I gave of
这张在第一节课中出现过的图
the successive neural nets. It's the same picture.
这是我给出的一系列神经网络的例子
Back then, I said we could get down to 20.7% by pre-training and then fine
当时我说我们通过预训练+反向传播调优
tuning with back propagation, and that the previous, and that the previous speak
把错误率降低了 20.7% 在此之前
independent record on Timint was 24.4%. Which actually required averaging several
TIMIT 的记录是 24.4% 他们实际上
models. Lee Ding at Microsoft Research picked up
采用了把多个模型平均的方法 微软研究院的 Ding Li
at this result immediately and collaborated on improving it.
继续合作改进了这一结果
And this has led to a big change in speech recognition.
这引发了语音识别领域的巨大变革
If you look at this news story, it will refer you to a blog where the chief
如果你看到这些新闻
research officer for Microsoft is talking about the big improvements in speech
你可能会想到微软研究主管 在博客中讨论这些
recognition caused by using deep neural nets.
在博客中讨论 这些深度学习在语音识别领域 引发的巨大进步